window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Discrete_Mathematics - Probability_Theory — Slot 3 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Probability_Theory — Slot 3",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Suppose \\(X_{i}\\) for i =1,2,3 are independent and identically distributed random variables whose probability mass functions are \\(Pr[X_{i}=0]=Pr[X_{i}=1]=1/2\\) for i=1,2,3. Define another random variable \\(Y=X_{1}X_{2}\\oplus X_{3}, \\; where \\; \\oplus\\) denotes XOR. Then<br>\n\\(Pr[Y=0|X_{3}=0]=\\)_______________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "0.75",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8496/gate2015-3-51#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>The probability that two friends are born in the same month is ____ ? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2014)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(1/6\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(1/12\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1/144</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(1/24\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(1/12\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/15032/isro2014-37\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Let S be a sample space and two mutually exclusive events A and B be such that A\\(\\cup\\)B = S. If P(.) denotes the probability of the event, the maximum value of P(A)P(B) is ______ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "0.25",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2082/gate2014-3-48#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>The probability that a given positive integer lying between 1 and 100 (both inclusive) is NOT\ndivisible by 2, 3 or 5 is ______ . <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "0.259",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2014/gate2014-2-48#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Each of the nine words in the sentence \"The quick brown fox jumps over the lazy dog\" is\nwritten on a separate piece of paper. These nine pieces of paper are kept in a box. One of the pieces is drawn at random from the box. The expected length of the word drawn is\n_____________. (The answer should be rounded to one decimal place) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "3.8",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1954/gate2014-2-2#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>The security system at an IT office is composed of 10 computers of which exactly four are\nworking. To check whether the system is functional, the officials inspect four of the\ncomputers picked at random (without replacement). The system is deemed functional if at\nleast three of the four computers inspected are working. Let the probability that the system is deemed functional be denoted by p.  Then 100p= _____________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "11.85",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1953/gate2014-2-1#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Four fair six-sided dice are rolled. The probability that the sum of the results being 22 is \\(\\frac{X}{1296}\\). The value of X is _________ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "10",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1927/gate2014-1-48#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Suppose you break a stick of unit length at a point chosen uniformly at random. Then the expected length of the shorter stick is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "0.24",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1717/gate2014-1-2#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Let P(E) denote the probability of the occurrence of event E. If P(A)= 0.5 and P(B)=1 then the values of P(A|B) and P(B|A) respectively are <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0.5, 0.25</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>0.25, 0.5</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>0.5, 1</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1, 0.5</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>0.5, 1</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/45660/isro-2013-71\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Suppose p is the number of cars per minute passing through a certain road junction between 5 PM\nand 6 PM, and p has a Poisson distribution with mean 3. What is the probability of observing fewer\nthan 3 cars during any given minute in this interval? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2013)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(8/(2e^{3})\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(9/(2e^{3})\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(17/(2e^{3})\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(26/(2e^{3})\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(17/(2e^{3})\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/62/gate2013-2#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Suppose a fair six-sided die is rolled once. If the value on the die is 1, 2, or 3, the die is rolled a\nsecond time. What is the probability that the sum total of values that turn up is at least 6? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2012)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(10/20\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(5/12\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(2/3\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(1/6\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(5/12\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1751/gate2012-33#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Consider a random variable X that takes values +1 and -1 with probability 0.5 each. The values of\nthe cumulative distribution function F(x) at x = -1 and +1 are <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2012)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>0 and 0.5</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>0 and 1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>0.5 and 1</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>0.25 and 0.75</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>0.5 and 1</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1577/gate2012-21#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Three coins are tossed simultaneously. The probability that they will fall two heads and one tail is <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>5/8</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1/8</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2/3</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>3/8</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>3/8</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/52837/isro2011-61\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>A deck of 5 cards (each carrying a distinct number from 1 to 5) is shuffled\nthoroughly. Two cards are then removed one at a time from the deck. What is\nthe probability that the two cards are selected with the number on the first card\nbeing one higher than the number on the second card? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(1/5\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(4/25\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(1/45\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(2/5\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(1/5\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2136/gate2011-34#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Consider a finite sequence of random values \\(X=[x_{1},x_{2},...,x_{n}]\\). Let \\(\\mu _{x}\\)\nbe the mean\nand  \\(\\sigma _{x}\\)\nbe the standard deviation of X .Let another finite sequence Y of equal\nlength be derived from this as \\(y_{i}=a*x_{i}+b\\), where a and b are positive\nconstants. Let Let \\(\\mu _{y}\\)  be the mean and \\(\\sigma _{y}\\) be the standard deviation of this\nsequence. Which one of the following statements is INCORRECT? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Index position of mode of X in X is the same as the index position of mode of Y\nin Y.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Index position of median of X in X is the same as the index position of median\nof Y in Y.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\mu _{y}=a\\mu _{x}+b\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\sigma _{y }=a\\sigma _{x}+b\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\sigma _{y }=a\\sigma _{x}+b\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2135/gate2011-33#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
